<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-20T15:30:45+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Paolo Facchinetti’s website</title><subtitle>Personal blog. I talk about open source software, trading and cryptocurrencies.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Generative Art as Non-Fungible-Tokens on Ethereum</title><link href="/crypto/generative-art-ethereum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generative Art as Non-Fungible-Tokens on Ethereum" /><published>2021-01-21T18:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T18:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/crypto/generative-art-ethereum</id><content type="html" xml:base="/crypto/generative-art-ethereum">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Generative art refers to art that in whole or in part has been created with the use of an autonomous system. An autonomous system in this context is generally one that is non-human and can independently determine features of an artwork that would otherwise require decisions made directly by the artist. In some cases the human creator may claim that the generative system represents their own artistic idea, and in others that the system takes on the role of the creator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generative art has been around for as long as computers were, making its first appearance in 1965 thanks to the work of &lt;a href=&quot;http://dada.compart-bremen.de/item/agent/15&quot;&gt;Georg Nees&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://dada.compart-bremen.de/item/agent/68&quot;&gt;Frieder Nake&lt;/a&gt;.
It’s only natural that an artistic process so dependent on technology would drastically change with the evolution of the tools it relies on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethereum in particular has been widely considered as the de-facto standard for Tokenized artworks, also called NFTs (Non-Fungible-Tokens), using the ERC-721 standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;nfts&quot;&gt;NFTs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFTs or Non-Fungible-Tokens are Ethereum tokens following the ERC-721 standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have never used Ethereum tokens, you can think of them as objects (as in traditional OOP objects) on the Ethereum blockchain, often used to represent something that can be money, data, or something more complex such as a share of ownership of an organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFTs in particular are tokens that represent an artwork, that can be an image, a video or even 3D models that are rendered in real-time (rendering is done off-chain, based on properties stored inside the on-chain token).
They are called &lt;strong&gt;“non fungible”&lt;/strong&gt; because each instance of a NFT is unique and not interchangeable like other &lt;strong&gt;fungible&lt;/strong&gt; assets would be (think of money, Bitcoin or even Ether).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;artblocks&quot;&gt;ArtBlocks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://artblocks.io&quot;&gt;ArtBlocks&lt;/a&gt; has become my favorite platform for the distribution generative art. From their website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Art Blocks is a first of its kind storefront for genuinely programmable on demand generative content that is stored immutably on the Ethereum Blockchain. You pick a style that you like, pay for the work, and a randomly generated version of the content is created by an algorithm and sent to your Ethereum account. The resulting piece might be a static image, 3D model, or an interactive experience. Each output is different and there are endless possibilities for the types of content that can be created on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each project released on ArtBlocks is coming from a different artist, which creates a generative script that is then stored on the Ethereum blockchain. Users can then iterate over the script from the ArtBlocks’ website by sending transactions to the smart contract, until a threshold of mints is reached (i.e. after 1000 artworks created, no more will &lt;strong&gt;ever&lt;/strong&gt; be created).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/singularity.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;One of the NFTs distributed by ArtBlocks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ArtBlocks has been experiencing an insane growth over the past two months since its inception. Releases are sold out in minutes regardless of high or low Ethereum gas fees (each mint costs approximately $20-40 in gas fees + the actual price of the NFT) and the secondary market on OpenSea is thriving, with some of the rarest artworks being sold for over $10.000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mechanism of randomness from traditional generative art is translated and gamified in a revolutionary way. The added thrill of not knowing how your NFT will look and the (relatively) low price of some releases encourages multiple mintings in the hope to find your &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; NFT and reminds me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gacha_game&quot;&gt;gacha games&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve personally been addicted to minting Chromie Squiggles, the first project released by ArtBlocks’ creator himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/chromie-squiggle.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A Chromie Squiggle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly suggest checking the platform out, but remember to not treat NFTs as investments. They are infinitely better (and more fun!) when you approach them as collectables or traditional artworks you would buy not for speculation, but for personal enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="crypto" /><summary type="html">Generative art refers to art that in whole or in part has been created with the use of an autonomous system. An autonomous system in this context is generally one that is non-human and can independently determine features of an artwork that would otherwise require decisions made directly by the artist. In some cases the human creator may claim that the generative system represents their own artistic idea, and in others that the system takes on the role of the creator.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DeFi: The bleeding edge of Blockchain and Web3</title><link href="/crypto/defi-bleeding-edge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DeFi: The bleeding edge of Blockchain and Web3" /><published>2020-09-04T09:42:53+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T09:42:53+01:00</updated><id>/crypto/defi-bleeding-edge</id><content type="html" xml:base="/crypto/defi-bleeding-edge">&lt;p&gt;Decentralized Finance (also known as &lt;strong&gt;DeFi&lt;/strong&gt;) is &lt;em&gt;an ecosystem of financial applications built on top of blockchain networks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
But what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t familiar with modern blockchain applications such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/dapps/&quot;&gt;Ethereum’s Decentralized Applications&lt;/a&gt; (or dApps), think of them as open source, distributed applications or services that are accessible by anyone that has access to the internet and has an Ethereum wallet.&lt;br /&gt;
The DeFi ecosystem is made of dozens of different dApps that share the objecting of porting and improving financial instruments to the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably sounds very vague to anyone that isn’t familiar with dApps, so let’s look into a DeFi application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;aave-protocol---money-markets-on-the-ethereum-blockchain&quot;&gt;Aave Protocol - Money Markets on the Ethereum blockchain&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aave.com/&quot;&gt;Aave&lt;/a&gt; is a protocol built on Ethereum that enables the creation of money markets. Users can lend or borrow assets through these markets, and earn interest on their deposits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds familiar to you? Probably so, because that’s the basic definition of loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why should you go through the trouble of using Aave, possibly with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stablecoin&quot;&gt;stable coins&lt;/a&gt; (crypto assets pegged to the US Dollar), instead of just using the services offered by your bank?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll let the numbers do the talk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/personal-finance/banks-pay-highest-interest-rates-savings-accounts/&quot;&gt;Investopedia&lt;/a&gt;, as of September 2020, the highest bank yearly interest rates are around 1.00% to 1.10%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Currently, Aave offers around &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.aave.com/home&quot;&gt;12% yearly returns&lt;/a&gt; on the stablecoin DAI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-bleeding-edge&quot;&gt;The Bleeding Edge&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a theoretical standpoint, DeFi sounds awesome.&lt;br /&gt;
It offers much, much better returns than traditional finance and it’s only getting started!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the drawdown?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, like many technological innovations, DeFi is considered to be on the bleeding edge of crypto and Web3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Bleeding edge technology is a category of technologies so new that they could have a high risk of being unreliable and lead adopters to incur greater expense in order to make use of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean?&lt;br /&gt;
For starters, that you should be extremely careful when using DeFi dApps.&lt;br /&gt;
Like all bleeding edge technologies, DeFi consists of experimental tech that hasn’t really passed the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how much money is locked in these protocols (as of September 2020, over &lt;strong&gt;8 billion USD&lt;/strong&gt;!), hackers are incentivized to look for bugs to exploit, and new scams are perpetrated each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, last June the DeFi protocol Balancer was &lt;a href=&quot;https://cointelegraph.com/news/defi-protocol-balancer-hacked-through-exploit-it-seemingly-knew-about&quot;&gt;hacked&lt;/a&gt; for over &lt;strong&gt;$500.000&lt;/strong&gt; in cryptocurrencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is the risk that it takes to be on the bleeding edge.&lt;br /&gt;
Venture capitals like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threearrowscap.com/&quot;&gt;Three Arrows Capital&lt;/a&gt; and single investors that have decided to speculate on Decentralized Finance have decided to face these risks, and have experienced tremendous returns in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, the Aave token has experienced a rise in its market price of an outstanding &lt;strong&gt;4000%&lt;/strong&gt; in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-defi-vips&quot;&gt;The DeFi VIPs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To end this blog post, if you’re interested in learning more about DeFi, I highly suggest watching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VT0enNGV78s&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;DeFi Roundtable from Smartcon 2020&lt;/a&gt; to see what the DeFi industry leaders think of the current state of Decentralized Finance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="crypto" /><summary type="html">Decentralized Finance (also known as DeFi) is an ecosystem of financial applications built on top of blockchain networks. But what does this mean?</summary></entry></feed>